<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>drone on isiko404's Homepage</title><link>https://isiko.github.io/tags/drone/</link><description>Recent content in drone on isiko404's Homepage</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 09:27:26 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://isiko.github.io/tags/drone/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Flying FPV</title><link>https://isiko.github.io/projects/fpv/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 09:27:26 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://isiko.github.io/projects/fpv/</guid><description>First-person view (FPV for short) drones, sometimes called racing drones, are the other kind of drones that most people have never heard of. They differ in almost all respects from the &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; camera drones known from manufacturers like DJI or Parrot. While the Parrot drone takes care of most of the flight control, here the pilot has to take care of the stabilization of the drone.
What seems like a big disadvantage at first glance is actually quite an advantage for FPV drones: With the extended level of control from the pilot, the pilot also has more options of what he can do with the aircraft.</description><content>&lt;p>First-person view (FPV for short) drones, sometimes called racing drones, are the other kind of drones that most people have never heard of. They differ in almost all respects from the &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; camera drones known from manufacturers like DJI or Parrot. While the Parrot drone takes care of most of the flight control, here the pilot has to take care of the stabilization of the drone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What seems like a big disadvantage at first glance is actually quite an advantage for FPV drones: With the extended level of control from the pilot, the pilot also has more options of what he can do with the aircraft. For example, a flip on a conventional drone can only be done using a button pre-programmed by the manufacturer, while doing tricks over and around obstacles is one of the biggest parts of FPV drones, referred to as freestyle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Of course, this also means that not every flight ends in a clean landing, for example, there is no controlled automatic landing sequence as with DJI, instead of which the motors are simply switched off, but this has also developed an advantage; because it is clear that the drones will probably be crashed, they are also built with this in mind. In most cases, every part is individually replaceable, from the propellers to the flight computer. Even the software in most cases open source, which means that it can write with, or even simply create its own version with its own features, if he is missing something in the official version.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="my-journey-to-the-world-of-fpv">My Journey to the World of FPV&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>It all started last year with the introduction of the DJI FPV. With this drone, DJI wanted to enter the FPV drone market, which for the first time gave people the opportunity to have a smooth transition from normal flying to full acrobatic mode without having to practice for hours in a simulator, which is usually the first thing new FPV pilots have to do.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I think the first time I saw this was in this video from MKBHD:
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/syiQmaGZFXM" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I loved the drone, but then I looked at the price tag of about 1600€ and sighed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few weeks later. My friend who had sent me the video was asked to produce an interactive video for our school to virtually show the new students around, since they couldn&amp;rsquo;t visit themselves because of Covid. The idea was to have a sparrow named Tom to show the students around. So we needed shots from the bird&amp;rsquo;s point of view flying over the school. That wasn&amp;rsquo;t a problem, we had done drone footage of the school in the past, but now we didn&amp;rsquo;t want just any drone footage, we wanted a bird flying around the school. The thing about normal drones is that they can do exactly one thing: take stable shots. You can definitely add some wobble in post-processing, but it won&amp;rsquo;t look as good. So to simulate a bird, we had to get an FPV drone, and somehow my friend convinced the school to buy us a DJI FPV system.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="center" >
&lt;img src="https://isiko.github.io/img/posts/fpv/testFlight.jpg" alt="The Drone, flying over a grass field" />
&lt;figcaption class="center" >Of course we had to take it for a test flight&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>That was when I started looking for a drone for myself. I knew I couldn&amp;rsquo;t afford a DJI FPV, but there had to be an option for me, and there was! I ended up getting what is called a Tiny Whoop. These drones are no bigger than the palm of your hand, but this allows them to be flown indoors and near people, which is great because then you can practice around the house without potentially losing the drone in a field. They are also incredibly cheap, I paid around 160€ for a complete kit with &lt;a href="https://betafpv.com/products/vr02-fpv-goggles">goggles&lt;/a>, a &lt;a href="https://betafpv.com/products/literadio-2-se-radio-transmitter">remote control&lt;/a> and the &lt;a href="https://betafpv.com/products/beta65s-bnf-micro-whoop-quadcopter">drone&lt;/a>, while the bigger drones usually start at around 300€.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I started flying indoors and annoying my family while I slowly dismantled the drone. Eventually, though, I wanted to do more. The problem was that you can&amp;rsquo;t really do any tricks with these tiny drones because they don&amp;rsquo;t have the power to catch themselves after a short fall. They also lose momentum pretty quickly because of their light weight and if you wan&amp;rsquo;t to do some long range stuff with them, no chanche because there isn&amp;rsquo;t enough place to but a decent reciever on these tiny tiny drones. So I went ahead and got a full 5&amp;quot; Quad. There were a few problems with the receiver and I had to change my radio, but now I can even fly a bit far as long as there is a clear view.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And this is exactly where I am now! Right now I&amp;rsquo;m flying more in the simulator because it&amp;rsquo;s pretty cold out right now, but come summer I&amp;rsquo;ll be back in the field, at least I hope so. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to post updates here when something interesting happens.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>